Guide to the James Hazen Hyde Papers 1874-1940, 1953 MS 319
New-York Historical Society
- Series I. General Correspondence, 1878, 1892-1939, 1953; 5.1 Linear feet in 13 boxes and one oversize folder
  - Photographic Negative of Unidentified Object, Undated (Box 8, Folder 41)
    This negative was found during processing in 2018 at this point in the collection. It is not apparent what, if any, connection there is but the item was left as found.
  - Monaco (Prince & Princesse de), 1917-1922 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Monvel, Bernard Boutet de, 1909-1924 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Monvel, Maurice Boutet de, 1899-1912 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Monvel, Roger Boutet de, 1912-1914 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Morris, Gouverneur, 1915-1917 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Mounet-Sully, 1909-1912 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Moure, E.J. (Docteur), 1910-1931 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Munsey, Frank A., 1919-1921 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - N. Miscellaneous, 1917-1935 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    Correspondents are Brigadier General D.E. Nolan, General Nogues, General Nollet, General Nivelle, Leon Noel, and Pol Neveux.
  - Nettleton, George H., 1918, 1928-1931 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    Concerns Nettleton's lectures in France sponsored by the Hyde Foundation. Some of the documents refer to the history of these lectures and Hyde's involvement.
  - Nolhac, Pierre de, 1903-1926 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Norton, C. E. and Grace, 1897-1898, undated (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Norton, Lawrence H., 1911-1924 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - O. Miscellaneous, 1910, 1915 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    Correspondents are the aide-de-camp of Prince Georges Romanowsky and John Ball Osborne. Mention of a tour of the World War I battlefront.
  - O'Brien, Morgan J., 1901-1908, 1918 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    Concerns payment of a loan from the Equitable (1903), attempts by O'Brien to assist in arranging lectures (1907-08), a letter of introduction (1918), and other matters.
  - Ochs, Adolph S., 1899-1935 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    Concerns advertising by Equitable in the Times (1899); the possibility of the Times establishing an international bureau (1900); a letter from Thomas Dewitt Cuyler regarding perceived antagonism toward the Pennsylvania Railroad by the Philadelphia Times (1901); and the Times's plans to move to a new location, the paper's financial status, encouragement to invest in the funding of the new building, the mortgage Equitable holds on the property, and aspects of the building's design (1902-04). Later correspondence (1908-35) mostly concerns letters of introduction, pleasantries, and compliments on written articles.
  - Ollivier, Emile, 1904 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Orliac, Marie d', 1913-1914 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Osler, William, 1908-1919 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    Concerning the acquisition of books, particularly antique books in London, and invitations and pleasantries. Also asked for Hyde's assistance in enrolling his son in school in London.
  - P. Miscellaneous, 1901-1934 (Box 9, Folder 20)
    Correspondents include, among others, Ferid Damad Pacha, Frank Puant, Comte Primoli, Georges Pallain, General Pelle, Ernest Perrin, Robert Pinot, Leon Pissard, Claude Pupier, Jean Psichari, M. Prou, Jean Pozzi, Monsieur de Pouydraguin (Comite France-Amerique), Francois Picavet, G. Perrot, H. Poincare, Ferdinand W. Peck (asking Hyde to be on a committee of arrangements for a banquet honoring French ambassador Jules Cambon in Washington), and Frederic C. Penfield. Discussion of a book on motoring (driving) in Spain. Menu for dejeuner at Presidence de la Republique (1 October 1918).
  - Painleve, Paul, 1915-1928 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Paleologue, Maurice, 1910-1919 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Parker, Gilbert, 1915 (Box 9, Folder 23)
    Transmittal letters for pamphlets and other print matter to Hyde.
  - Peabody, Endicott, 1916-1918 (Box 9, Folder 24)
    Hyde begins arranging to have his son attend Groton. Other letters with Peabody concern European travel.
  - Pelliot, Paul, 1914, 1928-1930 (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Perate, Andre, 1919-1931 (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Perkins, Dexter, 1911-1913 (Box 9, Folder 27)
    Primarily concerns Perkins's fellowship at the Ecole des Sciences Politiques and his descriptions to Hyde of travels in Italy, northern Africa and Russia.
  - Pernot, Maurice, 1915-1929 (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - Perry, Bliss (Mr & Mme), 1909-1914, 1927, 1932 (Box 9, Folder 29)
    Extensive correspondence from 1909-14 concerning Perry's lectures in France (arrangements, subject matter, reception in the various cities, plans to publish French translations of the lectures). In his letters to Perry, Hyde provides a great deal of historical context about these lectures. The correspondence largely ends in 1912. The few later letters include a request from Hyde for a letter of introduction (1914), request from Hyde for information about the Swiss school (Bellerive Institute) to which Perry had sent his son (1927), and a letter from Rachel Perry to the new Mrs. Hyde with very expressive congratulations on her marriage (1932) (see also Ralph Perry folder for other letters from Rachel).
  - Perry, Ralph Barton, 1921-1935 (Box 9, Folder 30)
    Also includes letters from Rachel Perry.
  - Pershing, John J. (General), 1917-1921 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    Hyde proposes to Pershing that an information bureau be created for university men coming to France (1917). This matter does not appear to be answered in these letters; the others are primarily invitations, thanks, greetings and pleasantries.
  - Persil, Raoul, 1914-1925 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Petain (Maréchal), 1916-1920 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Phipps, Eric (Sir), 1927-1933 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    Primarily invitations, congratulations on appointments, letters of introduction requests, and greetings, but also describes a James H. Hyde traveling scholarship awarded by the Royal Society of Arts.
  - Picard, Emile, 1929-1932 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Pichon,Stephen, 1907, 1913-1919 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Pierce, Daniel T., 1918-1930 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Pierson, Blanche, 1907-1919 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Platt, T.C. (U.S. Senator), 1901, 1903 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    Platt confirms to W.H. McIntyre that an award will be given the Cercle Francaise de l'Universite Harvard (1901). a frank of the National Express Company is given to Hyde (1903). Platt is asked to intercede with the Secretary of the Treasury for the National Bank of Commerce to continue as a depositary of funds, but finds that this need no longer exists (1903).
  - Poincare, Lucien, 1910-1920 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Poincare, Raymond, 1916-1926 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Polos (Federation des Polos de France), 1922 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    The principal correspondent is General de Serrigny.
  - Porche, Francois, 1926-1929 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Porter, Horace (General), 1903-1907 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    Primarily concerns the farewell banquet for Ambassador Porter given at the Hotel du Palais d'Orsay by the American "colony" in Paris (Hyde was on the Arrangements Committee). Includes the program/menu, clippings of news coverage, and correspondence.
  - Prevost, Marcel, 1907-1935 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - R. Miscellaneous, 1913-1931 (Box 10, Folder 16)
    Correspondents are Royal Military College (in connection with Hyde's gift of a bronze replica of Marshal Foch's death mask); Monsieur Regnault; Leon Renier; Louis Renault; A. Romanof(?); Henry Roujon; M. Ractivay(?); Gaston Rageot; Salvagio Raggi; Theodore Roosevelt (two invitations to receptions at the White House, 1903 and 1904; a typed letter signed and marked up by Roosevelt on Metropolitan letterhead in which he tells Hyde that if he should go abroad it would be best not to attend a banquet for him, at least until the war is over (May 10, 1917); Philippe Roy; Warren Delano Robbins; Alfred Richard (regarding the Foch death mask); Richard C. Richardson, Jr.; A. Ribot; Royal Society of Literature (M.H. Wagstaff).
  - Raleigh, Walter A., 1914-1917 (Box 10, Folder 17)
    Primarily concerns Hyde's interest in joining the Bibliographical Society of London, and in getting information from Raleigh about placing his young son in an English public school, with Eton and Winchester under discussion.
  - Reau, Louis, 1924-1931 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Reay (Mr & Mme/Lord & Lady), 1910-1914 (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Recouly, Raymond, 1915-1932 (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Regnier, Henri de (Mr & Mme), 1900-1912, 1933 (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Reinach, Joseph, 1910, 1912-1916 (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - Reinach, Salomon, 1911-1932 (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Reinach, Theodore, 1916-1928 (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - Rejane (Madame), 1907-1919 (Box 10, Folder 25)
  - Revue de Deux Mondes - Centenaire, 1929 (Box 10, Folder 26)
    The folder holds tickets, invitations, programs, menus and other ephemera related to the celebration of this centennial anniversary. Also holds some news clippings about it, including one referring to the fact that Hyde would speak at an event. An edited speech (in French) in the file is likely Hyde's remarks. Three letters are to/from Marcel Bouteron. See also the Rene Doumic folder.
  - Reynaud, Paul, 1917-1930 (Box 10, Folder 27)
  - Richepin, John, 1908-1919 (Box 10, Folder 28)
    Among other subjects, makes reference to Winthrop Ames and the New Theatre (in French).
  - Robertson, William, 1919-1920 (Box 10, Folder 29)
  - Robilant, Marie de (General), 1918-1919 (Box 10, Folder 30)
  - Roberts, Elmer, 1913-1931 (Box 10, Folder 31)
    Correspondent from The Associated Press's Paris Bureau. The 1915 letter includes a small photograph of Roberts; in his 1914-18 letters, Roberts comments on news he is hearing of military and diplomatic matters; from 1920-25, Roberts offers general thoughts about his meeting with Clemenceau and other matters; Roberts seeks to find information about French loans to America during the American Revolution and Hyde provides the detail.
  - Robinson, Edward & Elisabeth, 1899-1903, 1921-1925 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    Primarily concerns Hyde's donations (Union Library in Boston, 1901, and Lythgoe's Egyptian expedition, 1925) or potential donations (University Club, Boston, 1899) to various cultural projects. Also Hyde requests a reference for a researcher for his book on allegories; Robertson provides the name of Phila C. Nye. Most letters are from Edward; two undated letters are from Elisabeth.
  - Rockefeller, Jr., John D., 1910, 1916-1922 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    Primarily includes letters of introduction and related matters. Most substantively, Rockefeller introduces Hyde to Dr. Robert (or Richard) W. Corwin of the Colorado Fuel & Iron Company's Hospital. Rockefeller explains Corwin's mission to Europe to study the work of Doctors Carrel and Dakin to seek ideas for aiding those injured in mines; Hyde reports briefly back on Corwin's visit (1916). Rockefeller's letters date from 1916-18 and 1922. There are two 1910 notes from Edith Rockefeller McCormick, and these are generally courtesies.
  - Rod, Edouard, 1903-1908 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Rodin, Auguste, 1904(?)-1912 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Ronciere, Charles de la, 1922-1931 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Roussillon, Jean, 1931-1932 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    Also includes a copy of one letter from Berthelot to Andre Tardieu.
  - Roz, Firmin, 1912-1929 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    Includes, among many other matters, notes on a meeting with Kingsley Porter (1923).
  - Russell, Henry, 1909-1916 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Ryan, Thomas Fortune, 1903-1906, 1917 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    Early correspondence appears to relate primarily to matters concerning directorships of a bank and to Hyde's appointment of certain Equitable stock in his will. Later (1917) letters from Hyde are letters of introduction.
  - S. Miscellaneous, 1902-1930 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    Correspondents are Victorien Sardou; J.H. Sears: E.L. Spiers; Eugene Schneider; Jonkheer R. de Marees van Swinderen; George Saunders; V.P. Snyder of the Western National Bank, on various international financial matters (1902); Comte de Saint Aulaire.
  - Sabine, Wallace C. & Jane K., 1916-1917 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    Seems to be concerned primarily with Sabine's involvement in medical and relief work, with Hyde offering support and introductions. Many of Sabine's letters are on the letterhead of the Clinique Miremont in Leysin. Included is a copy of a letter from Jerome Greene of the Rockefeller Foundation explaining their willingness to support any campaign against tuberculosis in France authorized by the government.
  - Sachs, Paul J., 1926-1935 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    Among other matters, Hyde acts as intermediary for arrangements to bring Adolfo Venturi to Harvard to give courses in the Department of Fine Arts (1927); request that Hyde approach Bernard Berenson to give seminars at Fogg (1927); Hyde reports in outline on travels in Germany, apparently with letters of introduction from Sachs (1928); Hyde requests Sachs to give a lecture tour in the French provinces, which Sachs agrees to (several letters regarding this matter, 1932 and later); Sachs, on his own and at Berenson's suggestions, asks Hyde for letters of introduction to and information about various collectors in France (1933).
  - Schiff, Jacob, 1896-1904 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    Primarily concerns financial matters, including investments in the Conried Metropolitan Opera Company and the Fifth Avenue Trust Co. Reference to directorships of the Western National Bank.
  - Schiff, Mortimer L., 1924-1930 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Serrigny, B. (General), 1917-1921 (Box 11, Folder 15)
    See also the folder Polos (Federation des Polos de France) for additional correspondence with Serrigny.
  - Sharkey, Joseph E., 1912-1934 (Box 11, Folder 16)
    Sharkey is a correspondent for The Associated Press, and the correspondence with Hyde primarily concerns their observations about people they meet and world affairs. In a 1913 letter, Sharkey offers observations of Governor Woodrow Wilson; from 1913-1921, Sharkey is in the Tokyo Bureau and writes about the war and other matters in the Pacific; from 1925-1934, Sharkey is in the Geneva Bureau and the exchanges relate to European affairs.
  - Sharp, George C., 1932 (Box 11, Folder 17)
    Concerns the possibility of acquiring a portrait of Sharp's father for the American Chancery.
  - Sharp, William G, 1915-1922 (Box 11, Folder 18)
    Primarily includes invitations, courtesies, letters of introductions and the like. Perhaps the most substantive is a February 1917 letter in which Ambassador Sharp expresses his full support for Woodrow's position on freedom of the seas.
  - Siegfried, Jules, 1902-1922, 1931-1935 (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Societe Francaise de Secours aux Blesses Militaires, 1915-1917 (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - Stillman, James, 1908, 1915, 1917 (Box 11, Folder 21)
  - Stokes, Anson Phelps, 1929, 1933 (Box 11, Folder 22)
    Stokes describes the Institute of International Education and requests a donation (1929), and Stokes notes the success in France of Paul Sachs's lectures, with other comments (1933).
  - Stone, Melville E., 1909-1924 (Box 11, Folder 23)
  - Storrs, Ronald (Sir), 1931, 1933 (Box 11, Folder 24)
  - Strong, Eugenie (Mrs. Arthur Strong), 1914-1933 (Box 11, Folder 25)
  - T. Miscellaneous, 1912 (Box 11, Folder 26)
    Holds one letter, from Thouvenel.
  - Talleyrand, Duchess de, 1911, undated (Box 11, Folder 27)
  - Tardieu, Andre (3 folders), 1906-1935 (Box 11, Folder 28-30)
  - Thenault, Georges (Capitaine), 1921-1933 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Thiebaut (at French embassies in Washington DC and in Bern), 1900-1903 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Thurwanger, Camille, 1907-1913 (Box 12, Folder 2A)
  - Tirard, Paul, 1919-1930 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Tittoni, T., 1916, 1918 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Townsend, Reginald T., 1918-1919 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Tucker, Mona, 1953 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    This standalone letter from Tucker to Hyde was found in N-YHS's institutional archives correspondence, and moved here by the processing archivist, which explains the outlying date.
  - Untermyer, Samuel, 1906-1908 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - V. Miscellaneous, 1902-1925 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    Correspondents are Comte de Vogue; Ernest Van Dyke; E.H. Vigier; Paul Valery; K.M. Venizelos; Comte de San Martino Valperga; Henry Vignaud; Howard Vyse.
  - Vacaresco, Helene, 1907(?), 1929, 1932 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Van de Vyvere, A., 1915-1916 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Van Dyke, Henry, 1908-1913, 1921-1922 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    Primarily concerns arrangements for Van Dyke's lectures in France.
  - Van Dyke, Paul, 1919-1929 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Van Tyne, Claude H., 1913 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Vanderbilt, Alfred & Margaret, 1901, 1907-1911 (Box 12, Folder 14)
    Concerns interest by Hyde in providing a prize for the Olympia Horse Show; there is also a letter concerning French interest in the New York Horse Show (1910-11). Holds two indentures/leases from Hyde to Alfred Gwynne Vanderbilt for a stable in New York (West 58th Street between Broadway and Seventh Ave), 1907, 1909. Confirmation from Vanderbilt that he has signed papers for Equitable business matters.
  - Veber, Pierre, 1906-1908, 1918-1926 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Venturi, A. (Senatore), 1925-1927 (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - W. Miscellaneous, 1906-1933 (Box 12, Folder 17)
    Correspondents include, among others, Edith Wharton (accepting a lunch invitation, 1915, and informing Hyde she advised Madame Borel to affiliate with Madame de Billy, 1917); W.A. White; Hugh Campbell Wallace; Post Wheeler; Morgan (?) Weinberg; Henri Welchinger; Henry White; Charles Wyndham.
  - Waddington, Mary King (Madame), 1907-1917 (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Ward, J.Q.A. (John Quincy Adams), 1899-1902 (Box 12, Folder 19)
    Primarily concerns the sculptor's work on a statuette of Hyde's father.
  - Watterson, Henry (Colonel & Mme), 1913,1916 (Box 12, Folder 20)
    Hyde provides a detailed itinerary for his recommended travels in France.
  - Weill, Felix, 1921-1927 (Box 12, Folder 21)
    Extensive correspondence, the bulk of which is in French. It appears to relate primarily to matters concerning the Federation de l'Alliance Francaise Aux Etats-Unis et au Canada. Weill is Secretary General and Hyde is a Vice-President; the letters from Weill are generally on Federation letterhead.
  - Westinghouse, George, 1901-1904 (Box 12, Folder 22)
  - Weygand (General), 1917-1933 (Box 12, Folder 23)
  - Wilson, A.H. Hutton, 1916-1917 (Box 12, Folder 24)
    3 letters primarily concerning Hyde's request that he and a John H. Finley (and their chauffeurs) be permitted to visit the British front; Wilson says permission needs to be granted through the British Military Attache instead of him.
  - Wilson, H.B. (Admiral), 1918 (Box 12, Folder 25)
  - Winthrop, Henry Rogers & Alice, 1909, 1921, 1929-1935 (Box 12, Folder 26)
    One letter relates to the Metropolitan Opera Company (1909). The other letters primarily concern an exchange of observations about relations between France and the U.S, and in the 1930s, observations about Germany and the European situation. References to Alice are to Winthrop's daughter and her engagement.
  - Wister, Owen, 1929, undated (Box 12, Folder 27)
  - Wolfe, Elsie de, 1919-1926 (Box 12, Folder 28)
    Primarily concerns de Wolfe recommending or commenting on certain furniture/decorative furnishings to Hyde.
  - Woods, Lawrence C., 1917-1918 (Box 12, Folder 29)
  - Zaharoff, Basil, 1927-1929 (Box 12, Folder 30)
  - Lecture at Nantes, 1917 July 4 (Box 12, Folder 31)
    Hyde's remarks were on the occasion of a celebration of the arrival of American troops in France. The folder holds his remarks, which are in French, and an English translation of them under the subject title "Franco-American Historical Relations from 1776 until 1914," which apparently was delivered the next day at Major General William Sibert's request to his officers. An oversize poster announcing the event was removed to an oversize folder.
  - Lecture at Nantes (2 of 2). Oversize, 1917 July 4 (Folder Oversize-Med)
    Oversize poster for the event.
  - Article "The Antithesis of Kaiserism: The Royal Return to Brussels", 1918 November (Box 12, Folder 32)
    An article or memoir written by Hyde describing his travels to Lille and elsewhere in Belgium shortly after the Germans left and as the royal family returned. In English.
  - "Lettres d'Alsace. Premiere lettre. L'Anniversarie de la Liberation Strasbourg", 1919 (Box 12, Folder 33)
    Article written by Hyde describing his travels in Strasbourg beginning 22 November 1919. In French.
  - Speech at the Centennial of the Ecole Centrale des Arts & Manufactures, Paris, 1929 May (Box 12, Folder 34)
    Text of Hyde's remarks, with related correspondence. In French.
- Series II. Correspondence with Annie Fitch Hyde, circa 1891-1922; .73 Linear feet in 2 boxes
  This series includes extensive correspondence, predominantly in English, between James Hazen Hyde (most commonly referred to here as "Caleb") and his mother, Annie Fitch Hyde (sometimes referred to here by her telegram name "Einna," which was the name used on the original files). There are a very few letters that are either from Hyde's father, Henry Baldwin Hyde, or include the father's notes added to some of Annie's letters. There are also a few letters to Hyde from his mother's caregivers, Camille (letters in French) and Rippe.
  The earliest correspondence preserved in these files is primarily letters from Annie to Hyde. These are generally undated but the context indicates that these largely date from the 1890s while Hyde is away at school. Annie's letters make clear that Hyde routinely wrote to her, and she reciprocated with short affectionate notes about family updates, health, travels, and the like. By about 1899, typed copies of Hyde's letters appear in the files and for the balance of the files, Hyde's outgoing letters predominate, with occasional telegrams from Annie. There is relatively little correspondence for about 1903-1906, but there are many carbon copies of Hyde's letters to his mother from about 1907 to her death in mid-1922. Hyde wrote regularly to his mother, and these letters place on emphasis on noting who he dined or socialized with throughout the week, though the letters seldom mention the substance of conversations at these meetings. Hyde traveled with some frequency and he wrote in some detail about these trips, including those to Singapore, Guatemala, and many locations in Europe and in France. He wrote of lectures he gave, observations during World War I (though, as he notes, these are constrained by the censors), assistance given to the Red Cross during the war, his health, and the growth of his child, Henry. A certain tension surfaces at times in the letters, particularly over financial matters, which include Annie's sales of real estate, Hyde's finances, investments, and their handling of the Henry Baldwin Hyde estate.
  The original order of the series was, roughly, reverse chronological. To facilitate use, the documents were rearranged to a chronological order. Undated letters, which are mostly from Annie and are likely from the 1890s-1900s, are in the opening folders. Pins were used extensively by Hyde to connect pages of documents; these were removed during processing so care should be taken during use not to mix the sheets up.
  - Correspondence with Annie Hyde (9 of 16 folders), circa 1891-1912, undated (Box 13, Folder 1-9)
  - Correspondence with Annie Hyde (7 of 16 folders), 1913-1922 (Box 14, Folder 1-7)
- Series III. Correspondence Concerning Federation de l'Alliance Francaise, 1898-1935 (bulk 1902-1908, 1922-1933); 1.67 Linear feet in 4 boxes
  Biographical / Historical